Okay, so let's talk about the definition
of project management now.
Okay, so let's define project management.
Now, PMI defines project management as the
application of knowledge, skills,
tools, and techniques to project
activities to meet project requirements.
Okay, so project management then is the
application of knowledge, skills,
tools, and techniques to project activities
to meet the project requirements.
So that is PMI's exact definition of
project management.
Now, key terms, three key terms here are
knowledge, skills, tools, and techniques.
So let's talk about each of these.
So knowledge, knowledge about what?
Well, this is a definition of project
management.
So it's a knowledge of project management.
It's a knowledge of managing your project,
right?
So it's understanding then, proceed.
It's understanding methodologies,
right?
There's many different methodologies out
there.
Different industries use
different project management
methodologies, and different
industries are managed differently.
An IT project is managed
very differently to a
construction project, and
a very simple example.
There's different methodologies involved.
So let's see, it's understanding, the
standards, project management standards.
It's understanding project management
methodologies and which
methodology to use, when.
So it's the application of that,
it's application of that knowledge.
And whose knowledge?
Well, since there's a definition
of project management,
generally the knowledge
of the project manager.
But anybody else involved in the project
as well, such as the project team,
team leads, customers, anybody that is
involved in the project.
So it's the application of knowledge, And
remember, knowledge is
progressively elaborated.
You're constantly learning more and more,
right?
As more information is
gathered, you're starting
off with high level, drilling
down into the details.
So it's a knowledge about project
management.
It's also the knowledge about the product,
about the industry that you're working in,
right?
It's about the process
and about the, basically it's
knowledge about anything and
everything regarding the project.
So it's the application of knowledge and
then skills.
What skill sets are we talking about here?
Well, again, all skill sets required to
manage a project.
So a skill set such as, I
mean, think about this,
what kind of skill sets do
project managers have?
They have interpersonal skills,
management skills, leadership skills,
networking, collaboration.
There's going to be conflict, so project
managers need to manage conflicts.
So it's going to be conflict management
skills.
empathy, all of these skills we're going
to be talking about.
In subsequent videos, we're going to be
mentioning and talking
about all of these skills.
Emotional intelligence, communication
skills, facilitation skills, right?
It's going to be many meetings
and focus groups and brainstorming
sessions that project managers
are going to be leading.
So they need to be able to facilitate
these meetings.
So all of these skills are going to play a
big major part in managing your project.
Now, the number one
job skill for a project
manager is generally
considered as communication.
That is why you hire a project manager to
communicate.
A project manager is someone
that can get tasks moving
along, right, that can get team
members working together.
Project manager is someone that can get
teams working together.
There's going to be conflicts within
teams.
So a project manager is someone that can
manage these conflicts.
Now, is a project manager a technical
expert?
For the purpose of the
PMP exam, you are going
to assume they are not a technical expert.
And generally in order
to manage a project, you
don't necessarily need
to be a technical expert.
Now, having said that though, in many
industries, in order to get to that
position, you need to be a technical
expert.
And that's perfectly fine, PMI are not
saying that's wrong.
That's not wrong in any way.
all the saying is even if you're a
technical expert you need to be a good
communicator project managers spend 90% of
their time communicating so you need to be
a good communicator right so project
manager then have these communication
skills if you're not a good communicator
you won't necessarily make a very good
project manager right i mean your skills
will still be required in other areas i
mean project manager is just one role on a
project right there are a many,
many roles on a project,
but in order to be a good
project manager, you need
to be a good communicator.
So that's one of the key skills for a
project manager is communication.
So again, project management then is the
application of knowledge, which is
progressively elaborated, skills,
and then tools and techniques.
So project managers need the tools and
techniques to manage their project.
Team members need tools and techniques to
do the work, right?
So appropriate tools.
Likewise, project managers
also need appropriate tools
and techniques for them to
be able to manage the project.
And all these tools and
techniques, skills we're
going to be talking
about in separate videos.